RYAN BISHOP

| 7 11:1 000 11 | EMPLOYER TO-DO |
|------------------------------------|-----------------------|
| rdbishop06@gmail.com | APPLICATION EVAL. |
| rdbishop19.github.io | PHONE SCREEN |
| github.com/rdbishop19 | HIRING MGR. INTERVIEW |
| n linkedin.com/in/ryandanielbishop | IN-OFFICE INTERVIEW |
| | FOLLOW-UP |

SKILLS

- Software:
 - Python, JavaScript, React, Django REST, SQL, HTML, CSS, Git, GitHub, JIRA, AutoHotkey
- Data Science:
 - Data-wrangling/data-analysis
 - Supervised machine learning
- Strengths
 - Creativity, critical thinking, problem solving
 - Teamwork, public-speaking, communication
 - Customer support/service
 - Agile, Lean/Six Sigma, project management

PROJECTS

DEBUG DOCKET Front-End Capstone (NSS)

Debugging is an important skill for any developer. But bugs can have a bad reputation, being **costly**, **stress-inducing**, and **annoying**. I built **DEBUG DOCKET** to approach software bugs with a growth mindset through *healthy time management*, *helpful analytics* and *team engagement*.

- Single-Page Application built utilizing React
 Hooks with full CRUD-functionality for tracking
 to-do list of bug tickets and auto-tracking time
 spent on each bug
- Automated timer utilizing time management Pomodoro® Technique for consecutive work/break periods with friendly reminders
- Find fellow developer colleagues and view & help with their reported bugs
- github.com/rdbishop19/Debug-Docket

TL;DRSS Back-End Capstone (NSS)

RSS news feed aggregator with a twist. Users can submit **"too long; didn't read"** (TL;DR) short summaries of the articles they've read for other users to view and read publicly, allowing other users to get better context of the articles in their feed.

- Django REST API + React (Hooks) client
- Full CRUD on user-submitted article summaries
- Scheduled background tasks fetch new content
- Sort articles by popularity/most recent
- Users can subscribe to feeds to curate home page
- github.com/rdbishop19/TLDRss

EDUCATION

NASHVILLE SOFTWARE SCHOOL

Full-stack software development bootcamp | Nashville, TN | Sep 2019 - Mar 2020

ILLINOIS COLLEGE

B.S. in Biology & Spanish | Jacksonville, IL | 2006 - 2010 Graduated summa cum laude

LITCHFIELD HIGH SCHOOL

Graduated Valedictorian | Litchfield, IL | 2002 - 2006

ABOUT

I learned about **software development** working previously in a customer-facing technical role in the food production industry. This position introduced me to **Statistical Data Analysis**, **Regression Analysis**, **Machine Learning**, and programming and database management (**Python/SQL**). Leveraging this technical experience and a decade of business experience, I transitioned into software development via **Nashville Software School**. I'm a **lifelong learner** and inspired by continuous improvement **principles**, software design **patterns**, and passionate **people**.

EXPERIENCE

SOFTWARE DEVELOPER

Nashville Software School | Nashville, TN | Sep 2019 - Mar 2020

Full-stack 6-month web development program encompassing both individual and group project learning and experience in software design and production.

Tech Stack: Python, Django, SQL, React, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, Git, GitHub

Group Projects:

- E-commerce site (Django REST/React): integrated authentication, managing user payment types, and product reports; wrote integration tests for API endpoints
- Workforce mgmt. tool (**Django**): built CRUD for managing computers in inventory
- Command Line Interface (Python) Implemented decorator functions to display consistently styled menu screens
- Personal dashboard Single-Page Application: 2 separate sprints, built first in Vanilla
 JavaScript, and again in React, both utilizing JSON-server for persistent data storage.
 Personally implemented UI/UX affordances for the Chat Messaging and Add a Friend features, and facilitated group-programming for user authentication.
- Nashville Itinerary Planner application: championed Eventbrite API for fetching local event data, and also wrote and refactored dynamic functions for displaying results data across all 4 unique API endpoints.
- Celebrity tribute static HTML page: organized Git/GitHub workflow with my team

FIELD APPLICATION SPECIALIST

Perten Instruments (a Perkin-Elmer company) | IL, TN | Aug 2013 - Sep 2019

Analytical instrument company providing solutions for food ingredient screening, formulation, process monitoring, and final product quality control.

Technical Support/Customer Service: installation, training, and troubleshooting of on-site analytical equipment and software, including near infrared (NIR) and rheology lab instruments, utilized for the functional and compositional analysis of grain, feed, food, flour, and seed products. NIR machines with installed regression models provide a customer solution that is fast, low-cost, and easy-to-use.

Data Science: creation of predictive NIR models using machine learning regression analysis with spectroscopy data via third-party and in-house data analysis tool-kits (**Unscrambler, SQL, Python, R**).

- Data-wrangling of customer spectroscopy data sets using Excel & Unscrambler software to match 3rd-party reference chemistry data
- **Regression models** utilizing *supervised machine-learning* (Partial Least Squares Regression and k-nearest neighbors algorithms)
- Installed/updated predictive models on customer equipment to improve accuracy and provide QA/QC process control
- Customer collaboration discussing predictive model & process control improvements
- **AutoHotkey scripts** automating standardized customer regression reports
- VBA automation scripts improving data analysis & data cleansing workflow
- Phone/remote desktop **customer support** to troubleshoot database and application issues
- Onsite multi-day customer training of analytical equipment and software
- Follow-up customer support/documentation

MEDICAL TECHNICIAN

Memorial Medical Center | Springfield, IL | Nov 2010 - Aug 2013

- Surgical Pathology: assisted Pathologists with preparing and processing surgical specimens and performed diener duties during autopsies
- Administrative: created new documentation to streamline onboarding for new hires